<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Bylaws of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians">
  <meta>
    <effective>1936-05-23</effective>
  </meta>
  <heading>Bylaws of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>I</num>
    <heading>Duties of Officers</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1</num>
      <text>The Chairman of the Tribal Council shall preside at all meetings of the Council. He shall also be the presiding officer at any general Council meeting which may be duly called in accordance with these Bylaws. He shall at all times have general supervision of the affairs of the Tribal Council and such matters as naturally pertain to the general welfare of the community. It shall also be the duty of the Chairman to countersign all checks against funds of the organization by the Treasurer. He shall vote only in case of a tie. The Chairman shall be an ex officio member of all subordinate boards and committees.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2</num>
      <text>In the absence of the Chairman, the Vice-Chairman shall preside at all meetings of the Tribal Council and shall act in his stead in all matters pertaining to the office of the Chairman.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3</num>
      <text>The Secretary shall keep an accurate record of all proceedings of the Tribal Council and furnish copies thereof to the Superintendent and the Commissioner of Indian Affairs. He shall attend to the keeping of the official records of the Tribal Council and shall be responsible for the prompt and efficient handling of all correspondence pertaining to the business of the Tribal Council and the Band. All official records of the Tribal Secretary shall be open to inspection by the members of the Band at all times. The Secretary shall be ex officio member of all subordinate boards and committees.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4</num>
      <text>The Treasurer will be the custodian of all funds in possession of the Band from any source. He shall be under bond to a surety company of recognized standing in an amount to be determined by the Tribal Council, such surety company and bond to be approved by the Commissioner of Indian Affairs. He shall keep an accurate record of all such funds and shall disburse the same in accordance with the vote of the Tribal Council and in accordance with this Constitution and Bylaws. The books of the Treasurer containing the financial status of the Band shall be open to audit and examination by the duly authorized officers of the Secretary of the Interior at all times.</text>
      <text>The records of the Treasurer shall be open to inspection by members of the Tribal Council and its officers.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5</num>
      <text>The subordinate officers, boards, and committees of the Tribal Council shall perform such duties as the Tribal Council shall provide, by resolution, from time to time.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>II</num>
    <heading>Oath</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1</num>
      <text>All officers when elected shall be duly installed and subscribe to an oath of office to support the Constitution of the United States and <cite doc="Constitution of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians of the State of Wisconsin">this Constitution (of the Bad River Band)</cite>. Such officers maybe sworn in by an officer qualified to administer an oath.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>III</num>
    <heading>Salaries</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1</num>
      <text>Tribal officials shall be paid such salaries from available Tribal funds as the Tribal Council shall decide. All proposals for salaried positions by the Tribal Council shall be referred to the Secretary of the Interior for final decision.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2</num>
      <text>The members of the Tribal Council, boards, and committees shall be paid for expenses incurred in the interest of the community when previously authorized by the Tribal Council.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>IV</num>
    <heading>Meetings</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1</num>
      <text>Regular meetings of the Tribal Council shall be held on the first Wednesday of each month, and at such other times as the Tribal Council may by resolution provide. Called meetings shall be held at the discretion of the Chairman or upon request of three (3) members of the Tribal Council. Three (3) days written notice shall be given to all Council members.</text>
      <text>All Tribal Council meetings shall be posted at least three (3) days prior to a meeting. Signs to be placed in all public places within the exterior boundaries of the Bad River Reservation.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2</num>
      <text>Five (5) members shall constitute a quorum.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3</num>
      <text>The Tribal Council shall proscribe such rules of order for its meetings as it desires.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>4</num>
      <text>The meetings of the Tribal Council, except executive sessions, shall be open to the Tribe as auditors.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>V</num>
    <heading>Adoption of Constitution and Bylaws</heading>
    <text>This Constitution and Bylaws, when ratified by a majority of the qualified voters of the Bad River Band of Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians of Wisconsin, voting at a special election called for the purpose by the Secretary of the Interior, provided that at least 30 percent of those entitled to vote shall vote in such election, shall be submitted to the Secretary of the Interior, and, if approved, shall be effective from the date of approval.</text>
  </container>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <strong>CERTIFICATION OF ADOPTION</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Pursuant to an order, approved April 13, 1936, by the Secretary of the Interior, the attached Constitution and Bylaws was submitted for ratification to the members of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians of the Bad River Reservation and was on May 23, 1936, duly adopted by a vote of 169 for and 113 against in an election in which over 30 percent of those entitled to vote cast their ballots in accordance with Section 16 of the Indian Reorganization Act of June 18, 1934 (48 Stat. 984), as amended by the Act of June 15, 1935 (49 Stat. 378).</text>
    <text>s/W.P. Bigboy, Chairman, Election Board</text>
    <text>s/William Denomie, Chairman, Tribal Council</text>
    <text>s/Fred Chisholm, Secretary</text>
    <text>s/J.S. Cavill, Superintendent</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
