<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>16</num>
  <heading>Fireworks</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>1600</num>
    <heading>Regulating the Use of Fireworks</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1600.1</num>
      <heading>INTRODUCTION</heading>
      <text>The following is the ordinance regulating the use of fireworks within the exterior boundaries of the Bad River Reservation.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.2</num>
      <heading>PURPOSE</heading>
      <text>The Bad River Band seeks to limit the noise and disruption caused by the indiscriminate use of fireworks at inappropriate times.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.3</num>
      <heading>SCOPE</heading>
      <text>The ordinance applies to all tribally controlled lands within the exterior boundaries of the Bad River Reservation.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.4</num>
      <heading>AUTHORITY</heading>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to Article VI, Section 1(q) of the Constitution and Bylaws of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.5</num>
      <heading>SEVERABILITY</heading>
      <text>If any portion of this ordinance is found to be invalid for any reason, the remaining portions of this ordinance shall remain in effect.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.6</num>
      <heading>DEFINITIONS</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>In this Chapter, "fireworks" means anything manufactured, processed or packaged for exploding, emitting sparks or combustion which does not have another common use, but does not include any of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Fuel or a lubricant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A firearm cartridge or shotgun shell.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A flare used or possessed or sold for use as a signal in an emergency or in the operation of a railway, aircraft, water craft or motor vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>A match, cigarette lighter, stove, furnace, candle, lantern or space heater.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A cap containing not more than one-quarter grain of explosive mixture, if the cap is used or possessed or sold for use in a device which prevents direct bodily contact with a cap when it is in place for explosion.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A toy snake which contains no mercury.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A model rocket engine.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Tobacco and a tobacco product.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A sparkler on a wire or wood stick not exceeding 36 inches in length that is designed to produce audible or visible effects or to produce audible and visible effects.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>A device designed to spray out paper confetti or streamers and which contains less than one-quarter grain of explosive mixture.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>A fuseless device that is designed to produce audible or visible effects or audible and visible effects, and that contains less than one-quarter grain of explosive mixture.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>A device that is designed primarily to burn pyrotechnic smoke-producing mixtures, at a controlled rate, and that produces audible or visible effects, or audible and visible effects.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>A cylindrical fountain that consists of one or more tubes and that is classified by the federal department of transportation as a Division 1.4 explosive, as defined in 49 CFR 173.50.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(n)</num>
          <text>A cone fountain that is classified by the federal department of transportation as a Division 1.4 explosive, as defined in 49 CFR 173.50.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.7</num>
      <heading>AUTHORIZED DAYS AND HOURS OF THE USE OF FIREWORKS</heading>
      <text>Under this Chapter the Tribal Council shall establish days and hours which authorize or prohibit the use of fireworks on the Bad River Reservation.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.8</num>
      <heading>RETAIL AND WHOLESALE SALE OF FIREWORKS</heading>
      <text>Reserved</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.9</num>
      <heading>AGE LIMIT FOR PURCHASE, SALE AND POSSESSION OF FIREWORKS</heading>
      <text>Reserved</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.10</num>
      <heading>PENALTIES</heading>
      <text>Violation of this ordinance shall carry a forfeiture of not more than $50.00 for the first offense; $100.00 for the Second offense within 3 years of the first offense; and $500.00 per incident, for three or more offenses within 3 years of the first offense. Violators are also subject to immediate confiscation of all fireworks in the immediate possession of the violator or violators.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1600.11</num>
      <heading>JURISDICTION</heading>
      <text>The Bad River Tribal Court shall have exclusive jurisdiction over violations and disposition of matters arising from this ordinance.</text>
      <annotations/>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
