<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>5</num>
  <heading>Gaming</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.01</num>
    <heading>Gaming Control</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.01.010</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Council finds that gaming revenues are essential to the provision of tribal governmental services, that direct tribal control through the central tribal administration is essential to the rational utilization of tribal funds generated by tribally-operated gaming, that tribal gaming revenues must be fully integrated into the tribe's annual financial planning; and that tribal governmental spending priorities must take precedence over individual or organizational funding requests in the utilization of gaming receipts.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.010 was formerly codified as 500.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <container>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">A</num>
      <heading>Introduction</heading>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.020</num>
        <heading>Title</heading>
        <text>This ordinance shall be known as the Gaming Control Ordinance.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.020 was formerly codified as 500.21</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.030</num>
        <heading>Authority</heading>
        <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to Article VI, Section 1(g) and (j) of the Constitution and Bylaws of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians.  All violations of this ordinance shall be prosecuted in Tribal Court.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.030 was formerly codified as 500.22</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.040</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this ordinance is to regulate the conduct of Class II and Class III gaming conducted on the Bad River Indian Reservation.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.040 was formerly codified as 500.23</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.050</num>
        <heading>Effective Date</heading>
        <text>This ordinance shall be effective on the date of enactment by the Bad River Tribal Council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.050 was formerly codified as 500.24</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.060</num>
        <heading>Abrogation and Greater Restrictions</heading>
        <text>Where this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in other tribal ordinances, the provision of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.060 was formerly codified as 500.25</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.070</num>
        <heading>Interpretation</heading>
        <text>In their interpretation and application, the provisions of this ordinance shall be held to be minimum requirements and shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe and shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other Tribal power or authority.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.070 was formerly codified as 500.26</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.080</num>
        <heading>Severability and Non-liability</heading>
        <text>If any section, provision or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby.  The Tribe asserts there is no liability on the part of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians, its agents or employees for damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon, and conformance with this Ordinance.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.080 was formerly codified as 500.27</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">B</num>
      <heading>Electronic Bingo</heading>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.090</num>
        <heading>General</heading>
        <text>Under 25 U.S.C. § 2703(7) of the IGRA, Class II games may utilize electronic, computer or other technologic aids. At the same time, IGRA strictly prohibits the use of electronic or electromechanical facsimiles of any game of chance without a tribal-state compact or procedures issued by the Secretary of the Interior.  Any Gaming System that is determined by the Tribal Gaming Commission not to be Class II may only be operated at the Tribal Gaming Facility pursuant to the terms of a tribal-state compact or Class III gaming procedures.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.090 was formerly codified as 500.31</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.100</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <text>For the purposes of <cite path="5.01|B">this subchapter</cite>, the following definitions shall be used.  Words in the present tense include the future; the singular includes the plural; and the plural includes the singular.  The word "shall" is mandatory and the word "may" is permissive.</text>
        <text>Electronic Bingo (Class II)</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>Definitions</strong>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text><strong>"Bingo"</strong> means the game of chance set forth in the IGRA at 25 U.S.C. § 2703(7)(A)(i), (whether or not electronic, computer, or other technologic aids are used in connection therewith):</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Which is played for Prizes, including monetary Prizes, with Cards bearing numbers or other designations;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>In which the holder of the Card covers such numbers or designations when objects, similarly numbered or designated, are drawn or electronically determined; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>In which the game is won by the first person covering a previously designated arrangement of numbers or designations on such Cards.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text><strong>"Card"</strong> means an array of numbers or other designations, presented on paper and/or in electronic form, that is used by a player as a basis to Cover such numbers or other designations drawn or electronically determined in a Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text><strong>"Claim"</strong> means a player's declaration of the right to a Prize under the Rules of Play.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text><strong>"Classification Determination"</strong> means a formal determination by the Tribal Gaming Commission that a Gaming System is Class II under this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text><strong>"Consideration"</strong> means the player's payment or credit to participate or to continue participating in a game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text><strong>"Council"</strong> or <strong>"Tribal Council"</strong> means the seven (7) member committee composed of elected tribal officials authorized to represent the Tribe pursuant to the Tribe's Constitution.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text><strong>"Cover"</strong> means the process of matching or daubing the numbers or other designations on a Card that correspond to numbers or other designations from a Draw.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text><strong>"Draw"</strong> means the physical or electronic selection of numbers or other designations from the set of numbers or other designations used to determine winners in a Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electronic, Computer or Other Technologic Aid"" </strong>has the meaning set forth in <cite path="5.01.130|(a)|(2)">Section 5.01.130(a)(2)</cite> of this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electronic or Electromechanical Facsimile" </strong>has the meaning set forth in <cite path="5.01.130|(a)|(3)">Section 5.01.130(a)(3)</cite> of this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text><strong>"Game Winning Card"</strong> means a Card on which a Game Winning Pattern has been Covered.  There may be more than one Game Winning Card in any Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text><strong>"Game Winning Pattern"</strong> means a specific array of numbers or other designations on a Card that, when Covered on the Card(s), entitles the player(s) to receive the Game Winning Prize.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Gaming Commission"</strong> means a Tribally designated entity responsible for Gaming regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text><strong>"Gaming System" </strong>means all components, including electronic, computer, or other technologic equipment, that function together to aid the play of one or more games of Bingo including any Player Interfaces.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text><strong>"NIGC"</strong> means the National Indian Gaming Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text><strong>"NIGC Technical Standards"</strong> means the Technical Standards for Electronic, Computer, or Other Technologic Aids Used in the Play of Class II Games, 25 C.F.R. Part 547.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text><strong>"Pattern"</strong> means, in the case of a Game Winning Pattern, an array of two or more numbers or other designations on a Card.  A Pattern for a Prize Winning Pattern must contain at least one number or other designation on a Card.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text><strong>"Player Interface" </strong>means any component or components of a Gaming System, including an electronic or technologic aid such as terminals, player stations, handhelds, fixed units, etc. that directly enables player interaction in a game of Bingo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize"</strong> means anything of material value, including money, which is awarded to a player under the Rules of Play.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize Pool" </strong>means the cumulative amount of contributions paid by participants in one of more games of Bingo, which is used to fund prizes specified in the Rules of Play.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize Winning Card"</strong> means a Card on which a Prize Winning Pattern has been Covered, entitling a player to Claim an interim or consolation Prize under the Rules of Play.  There may be more than one Prize Winning Card in any Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize Winning Pattern"</strong> means a specific array of numbers or other designations that, when Covered on a Card(s), entitles the player(s) to receive an interim or consolation Prize.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(23)</num>
            <text><strong>"Random Number Generator (RNG)"</strong> means an electronic or mechanical method for determining numbers or other designations in a game of chance that must meet the applicable standards for randomness set forth in the NIGC Technical Standards or established by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(24)</num>
            <text><strong>"Rules of Play"</strong> means the specific rules controlling the play of the subject game of Bingo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(25)</num>
            <text><strong>"Server" </strong>means a computer which controls one or more applications or environments within a Gaming System.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(26)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Gaming Facility"</strong> means the Casino, which is located on the Indian lands of the Tribe operated pursuant to the Tribe's Gaming Ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(27)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Gaming Facility Manager (TGFM)"</strong> means the Casino Gaming Manager who operates the gaming facility for the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.100 was formerly codified as 500.32</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.110</num>
        <heading>Classification Procedure</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Application Process</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Only a duly authorized representative of the GM may apply for a Classification Determination under this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The GM may apply for a Classification Determination at any time, but must do so before offering a new Gaming System for play under the following circumstances:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A</num>
              <text>The GM wishes to install a new Gaming System that is not the subject of an existing Classification Determination and is not otherwise permitted as a Class III game; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>The GM wishes to introduce a material modification to a previously approved Gaming System, including a Gaming system approved before the effective date of this Regulation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Although not required, the GM also may apply for a Classification Determination under this Regulation for a Gaming System approved by the Tribal Gaming Commission before the effective date of this Regulation.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Application Submission Requirements</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>To obtain a Classification Determination, the GM must submit an application to the Tribal Gaming Commission, which consists of the following documentation and information:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Request for a Classification Determination;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Certification by the vendor of the Gaming System that the Gaming System to be placed in the Tribal Gaming Facility:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Is within the criteria for a Class II game of Bingo under IGRA and this Regulation;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Complies in all respects with the specifications and standards set forth in the application<em>; </em>and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Complies with any applicable regulations concerning such Gaming System.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>A legal opinion that concludes that the Gaming System is a Class II game of Bingo under the IGRA played using a permitted electronic, computer or other technologic aids;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>GM's statement that, to the best of its knowledge and belief, the subject Gaming System meets the standards in these Regulations; [optional]</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>Designation of a point of contact authorized to provide additional information if required;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>Designation from the vendor of whether and where the Gaming System is already in play;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(G)</num>
              <text>Complete written description from the vendor of the Gaming System, including the operational characteristics and Rules of Play;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(H)</num>
              <text>Complete description of the method used for accepting Consideration from players, paying or distributing Prizes to winners, determining, retaining or paying any amounts to the operator or vendor from the Consideration or any other source, and the awarding or funding of Prize Pools;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>Copy of any of the vendor's sales or promotional literature for the Gaming System; [Optional]</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(J)</num>
              <text>For Gaming Systems already in play at the Tribal Gaming Facility, a complete list of the serial numbers or other identifiers of each Player Interface or other device used in the play of the Gaming System;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(K)</num>
              <text>Report of laboratory test(s), which must be addressed to the Tribal Gaming Commission, which were conducted that validate that the Gaming System meets the requirements of Sections B(1)(b)(ii) and (iii) of this Article, as well as the requirements of the NIGC Technical Standards found at 25 C.F.R. Part 547;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(L)</num>
              <text>Copies of any court or administrative decisions or other materials, supplied by the Gaming System vendor, which address the classification of the proposed Gaming System, if any;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submission of Additional Information</text>
          <text>Upon request of the Tribal Gaming Commission, the GM may be required to provide any further information or clarification the Tribal Gaming Commission deems necessary to make a Classification Determination.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.110 was formerly codified as 500.33</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.120</num>
        <heading>Classification Modifying Games</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Modification of Gaming Systems</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The GM shall submit to the Tribal Gaming Commission a request for a review of a Gaming System that is to be modified by providing a detailed description of the modification and how the modification affects the Gaming System.  If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that the modification represents a material change to the classification of the Gaming System, the GM must submit an application pursuant to part (2) of <cite path="5.01.120">this Section</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An application for a new Classification Determination shall not be required if the modification does not result in a material change to the operation of the Gaming System.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission shall maintain a list of modifications determined by the Tribal Gaming Commission to be non-material, which shall be updated periodically by the Tribal Gaming Commission as technology advances.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.120 was formerly codified as 500.34</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.130</num>
        <heading>Classification Criteria</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Factors to be Considered in Making Classification Determination</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The critical factors in determining whether a Gaming System is Class II are:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Whether the underlying game is a Class II game of Bingo; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Whether the electronic equipment utilized in connection with the game:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Is an electronic, computer or other technologic aid, which is permitted within Class II; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Causes the game to be an electromechanical facsimile of a game of chance.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An electronic, computer or other technologic aid:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Is defined as electronic, computer, or other technologic equipment used in connection with a game of Bingo that:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Assists a player or the playing of a game;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Is not an electromechanical facsimile; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Is operated in accordance with applicable federal communications law.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Includes, but is not limited to, electronic, computer, or other technologic equipment used in connection with a Bingo game that:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Broadens participation in the game;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Facilitates communication between and among gaming sites; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Requires a player to play a game with or against other players rather than with or against a machine.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Examples include, but are not limited to, telephones, cables, televisions, screens, satellites, bingo blowers, electronic player stations and electronic Cards.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>An electromechanical facsimile is a game played in an electronic or electromechanical format that replicates a game of chance by incorporating all of the characteristics of the game, except when for a Class II game such as Bingo, the electronic or electromechanical format broadens participation by allowing multiple players to play with or against each other rather than with or against a machine.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determination that Gaming System is Class II</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Bingo, as played using a Gaming System, will be determined to be a Class II game if it possesses the attributes of Bingo as set forth in the definition of Bingo in this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission has determined that the following attributes are required by the definition of Bingo:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The underlying game consists of:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>A set quantity of Draw numbers or other designations (hereinafter referred to as "Symbols");</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>A set number of Cards bearing an array or layout of numbers or other designations available for play in a particular game of Bingo;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Predetermined Game Winning Pattern(s); and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <text>Prizes, including a Game Winning Prize and optional interim and consolation Prizes, as defined under the Rules of Play<em>.</em></text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>The Draw, if conducted using a Random Number Generator, must meet applicable standards for ensuring randomness as set forth in the NIGC Technical Standards or established by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Actual Prize values must be defined before a Prize can be awarded, but need not be defined before the start of a game.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>A game must be played by a minimum of two players.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission has determined that the following attributes are consistent with, <u>but not required by</u>, the definition of Bingo:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The number of Symbols in a Draw is not fixed; it may be varied from game to game, in accordance with the Rules of Play.  Symbols may be displayed, without limitation, as numbers, letters, icons, any other graphic or other enhancement, or any combination thereof.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>A game may include any number of Cards.  The Card may be multi-dimensional.  Each Card must have an array or layout of symbols and contain at least two of the Draw symbols.  Game Winning Patterns and Prize Winning Patterns can be any configuration of matched symbols on the player's Card.  Interim and consolation Prizes also can be awarded for the absence of matched symbols.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>When playing Bingo, a Draw of a fixed number of Symbols may take place before Cards are purchased by, or distributed to, some or all of the players.  Players then compete in a given game by purchasing Cards and then revealing the designations on purchased Cards, so that the pre-drawn Symbols may be Covered.  Subsequent Draws may take place to assure that a Game Winning Pattern is achieved.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>Multiple Prizes may be specified in a game based on, but not necessarily limited to, different Patterns or the number of drawn Symbols required to achieve a specified Pattern.  There may be multiple winners, on multiple Cards.  Prize levels can also vary for the same Pattern as a function of the player's Consideration for the Card and/or how far the Draw has progressed.  Prizes may include interim or consolation Prizes where the Prize is based on the specific order in which the numbers are selected.  Progressive Prizes may also be awarded based on specified criteria reflecting sequence or specific characteristics of the Symbols Covered by the player.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>A player may play more than one Card in a game of Bingo.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>In determining whether Bingo, as played using a Gaming System, is a Class II game, the Tribal Gaming Commission should not apply any requirements that would:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Limit the use of electronic aids to play Bingo, display Cards, Cover Symbols, identify Game or Prize Winning Patterns, or Claim Prizes;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Limit the speed of play, Card configuration, or number of Draws in a game;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Limit how or when Cards are distributed to players;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>Limit the sequence of a Draw;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>Limit how a player Claims a Prize;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>Limit the type of entertaining display on the Player Interface; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(G)</num>
              <text>Limit the maximum number of players.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.130 was formerly codified as 500.35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.140</num>
        <heading>Classification Decisions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issuance of a Written Classification Determination</text>
          <text>If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that the Gaming System meets the criteria in Article 6 above, it shall issue a written Classification Determination and shall provide copies of such Classification Determination to the Tribal Council and the GM.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Issuance of an Unfavorable Determination</text>
          <text>If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that the Gaming System does not meet one or more of the criteria in Article 6 above, it shall issue a written decision specifically addressing the reasons for its determination and shall provide copies of such decision to the Tribal Council and the GM.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Finality of the Decision</text>
          <text>If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that a Gaming System is not Class II for any reason, the decision of the Tribal Gaming Commission will be final and binding. The Tribal Gaming Commission may, in its discretion, allow a request for reconsideration upon a showing of new factual evidence or legal support.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.140 was formerly codified as 500.36</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.150</num>
        <heading>Installation of Gaming Systems</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Confirmation of Specifications</text>
          <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission requires the manufacturer or distributor of Gaming Systems intended for use in this jurisdiction to certify, in writing, that prior to delivery to the Tribe, each Gaming System:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Conforms precisely to the exact specifications of the system prototype tested and approved by the test laboratory.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Can be tested using one or more unique signatures, checksum values or similar technology for the operating programs used with the electronic computer, or other technologic aid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Operates and plays in accordance with the NIGC Technical Standards, this Regulation and all other applicable Tribal Gaming Commission regulations.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Integrity of Seals</text>
          <text>Upon delivery of a Gaming System to the Tribal Gaming Facility, no one will break the seal of any delivery container, nor will any system be removed from the shipping container without the physical presence and authorization of a Tribal Gaming Commission official.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Use of Approved Locks</text>
          <text>The GM shall replace Player Interface locks with locks approved for use by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>System Modifications</text>
          <text>The GM shall develop policies and procedures to be approved by the Tribal Gaming Commission for installing, accessing, maintaining, repairing, and configuring systems in the same manner as set forth in Tribal Gaming Commission regulations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Delivery of Gaming Systems</text>
          <text>At least ten (10) calendar days prior to shipping and delivery of a Gaming System, each manufacturer or distributor shall report in writing to the Tribal Gaming Commission the following information for each Player Interface to be used as part of the Gaming System:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The type of Player Interface (i.e. hand-held or fixed-base).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Player Interface serial number.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The manufacturer of the Player Interface.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The vendor from whom the Player Interface was acquired,  the means by which the Player Interface will be transported into the state, and the name and street address of any common carrier or other person transporting the Player Interface.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The date of shipping and anticipated delivery date.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Notice of New or Upgraded Software</text>
          <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission shall be notified by the GM of any subsequent purchases of any new or upgraded program software within ten (10) calendar days.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.150 was formerly codified as 500.37</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.160</num>
        <heading>Labeling of Approved Gaming Systems</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Serial Numbers</text>
          <text>Once a Gaming System has been determined to be Class II, the GM will provide a serial number and description of each Player Interface to the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requirement for Seals or Labels</text>
          <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission shall affix a seal or a label on each of the internal components of each Player Interface to indicate proper determination. The seal or other label will be visible when the Player Interface door is open and will show the version number(s) or other unique identifier(s), as documented by the testing laboratory.  The seal or other label will be promptly removed from the Player Interface when the version number(s) of the software operated thereon are changed and a new seal or other label affixed showing the versions of the software in use; provided the new version(s) meet the standards established in this Regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.160 was formerly codified as 500.38</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.170</num>
        <heading>Amendment/Repeal of Regulation</heading>
        <text>This Regulation may be amended or repealed upon approval by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.170 was formerly codified as 500.39</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.180</num>
        <heading>Effective Date</heading>
        <text>This Regulation shall take effect immediately upon adoption as approved by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.180 was formerly codified as 500.39(a)</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <section>
      <num>5.01.190</num>
      <heading>Bingo (Non-Electronic)</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of <cite path="5.01.190">this chapter</cite>, the following definitions shall be used.  Words in the present tense include the future; the singular includes the plural; and the plural includes the singular.  The word "shall" is mandatory and the word "may" is permissive.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Bingo" means a game of chance in which players pay a consideration in order to participate, in which 75 numbered objects are available for selection, and those objects actually selected are selected on a random basis, and in which each player participates by means of cards sold, rented or used only at the time and place of the game, each card containing 5 rows of 5 spaces each, each space printed with a number from 1 to 75 except the central space, which is marked "FREE".  Winners are determined and prizes awarded on the basis of possessing a bingo card on which some combination of numbers are printed and conform to the number objects selected at random based on a predetermined winning arrangement.  "BINGO" as used in <cite path="5.01">this chapter</cite> shall not mean any game using free cards and donated prizes, if any, for which no payment of consideration is made by players.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Bingo Manager" means a person hired by the Tribe to conduct, organize and supervise all bingo and raffle occasions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"Bingo Occasion" means a single gathering or session at which a series of successive bingo games are played.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"Bingo Supplies and Equipment" means all cards, boards, sheets, markers, pads or other supplies, devices or other equipment designed for used in the conduct or play of bingo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>"Caller" means an individual who by means of a mechanical device randomly selects numbers and announces them to players.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>"Checker" means an individual who verifies a player's claim to have won a game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>"Class II Gaming" means class II gaming as defined by 25 U.S.C. §2703(7), including by not limited to bingo, raffles, and pull-tabs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>"Class III Gaming" means class III gaming as defined by U.S.C. §2703(8).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>"Council" means the governing body of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>"Inventory Checker" means a designated person from the accounting office who shall be responsible for a monthly inventory check of the bingo supplies/materials.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>"Raffle" means a game of chance in which tickets are sold and a drawing for prizes is held, or in which the ticket is drawn by the purchaser and a determination of prize made based upon the ticket drawn.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>"Reservation" means all lands within the exterior boundaries of the Bad River Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>"Tribe" means the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.190 was formerly codified as 500.4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
