<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Chippewa Indians Tribal Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>5</num>
  <heading>Gaming</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.01</num>
    <heading>Gaming Control</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.01.010</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Council finds that gaming revenues are essential to the provision of tribal governmental services, that direct tribal control through the central tribal administration is essential to the rational utilization of tribal funds generated by tribally-operated gaming, that tribal gaming revenues must be fully integrated into the tribe's annual financial planning; and that tribal governmental spending priorities must take precedence over individual or organizational funding requests in the utilization of gaming receipts.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.010 was formerly codified as 500.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <container>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">A</num>
      <heading>Introduction</heading>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.020</num>
        <heading>Title</heading>
        <text>This ordinance shall be known as the Gaming Control Ordinance.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.020 was formerly codified as 500.21</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.030</num>
        <heading>Authority</heading>
        <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to Article VI, Section 1(g) and (j) of the Constitution and Bylaws of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians.  All violations of this ordinance shall be prosecuted in Tribal Court.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.030 was formerly codified as 500.22</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.040</num>
        <heading>Purpose</heading>
        <text>The purpose of this ordinance is to regulate the conduct of Class II and Class III gaming conducted on the Bad River Indian Reservation.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.040 was formerly codified as 500.23</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.050</num>
        <heading>Effective Date</heading>
        <text>This ordinance shall be effective on the date of enactment by the Bad River Tribal Council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.050 was formerly codified as 500.24</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.060</num>
        <heading>Abrogation and Greater Restrictions</heading>
        <text>Where this ordinance imposes greater restrictions than those contained in other tribal ordinances, the provision of this ordinance shall govern.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.060 was formerly codified as 500.25</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.070</num>
        <heading>Interpretation</heading>
        <text>In their interpretation and application, the provisions of this ordinance shall be held to be minimum requirements and shall be liberally construed in favor of the Tribe and shall not be deemed a limitation or repeal of any other Tribal power or authority.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.070 was formerly codified as 500.26</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.080</num>
        <heading>Severability and Non-liability</heading>
        <text>If any section, provision or portion of this ordinance is adjudged unconstitutional or invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remainder of this ordinance shall not be affected thereby.  The Tribe asserts there is no liability on the part of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians, its agents or employees for damages that may occur as a result of reliance upon, and conformance with this Ordinance.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.080 was formerly codified as 500.27</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>Subchapter</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">B</num>
      <heading>Electronic Bingo</heading>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.090</num>
        <heading>General</heading>
        <text>Under 25 U.S.C. § 2703(7) of the IGRA, Class II games may utilize electronic, computer or other technologic aids. At the same time, IGRA strictly prohibits the use of electronic or electromechanical facsimiles of any game of chance without a tribal-state compact or procedures issued by the Secretary of the Interior.  Any Gaming System that is determined by the Tribal Gaming Commission not to be Class II may only be operated at the Tribal Gaming Facility pursuant to the terms of a tribal-state compact or Class III gaming procedures.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.090 was formerly codified as 500.31</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.100</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <text>For the purposes of <cite path="5.01|B">this subchapter</cite>, the following definitions shall be used.  Words in the present tense include the future; the singular includes the plural; and the plural includes the singular.  The word "shall" is mandatory and the word "may" is permissive.</text>
        <text>Electronic Bingo (Class II)</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>
            <strong>Definitions</strong>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text><strong>"Bingo"</strong> means the game of chance set forth in the IGRA at 25 U.S.C. § 2703(7)(A)(i), (whether or not electronic, computer, or other technologic aids are used in connection therewith):</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Which is played for Prizes, including monetary Prizes, with Cards bearing numbers or other designations;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>In which the holder of the Card covers such numbers or designations when objects, similarly numbered or designated, are drawn or electronically determined; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>In which the game is won by the first person covering a previously designated arrangement of numbers or designations on such Cards.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text><strong>"Card"</strong> means an array of numbers or other designations, presented on paper and/or in electronic form, that is used by a player as a basis to Cover such numbers or other designations drawn or electronically determined in a Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text><strong>"Claim"</strong> means a player's declaration of the right to a Prize under the Rules of Play.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text><strong>"Classification Determination"</strong> means a formal determination by the Tribal Gaming Commission that a Gaming System is Class II under this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text><strong>"Consideration"</strong> means the player's payment or credit to participate or to continue participating in a game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text><strong>"Council"</strong> or <strong>"Tribal Council"</strong> means the seven (7) member committee composed of elected tribal officials authorized to represent the Tribe pursuant to the Tribe's Constitution.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text><strong>"Cover"</strong> means the process of matching or daubing the numbers or other designations on a Card that correspond to numbers or other designations from a Draw.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text><strong>"Draw"</strong> means the physical or electronic selection of numbers or other designations from the set of numbers or other designations used to determine winners in a Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electronic, Computer or Other Technologic Aid"" </strong>has the meaning set forth in <cite path="5.01.130|(a)|(2)">Section 5.01.130(a)(2)</cite> of this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text><strong>"Electronic or Electromechanical Facsimile" </strong>has the meaning set forth in <cite path="5.01.130|(a)|(3)">Section 5.01.130(a)(3)</cite> of this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text><strong>"Game Winning Card"</strong> means a Card on which a Game Winning Pattern has been Covered.  There may be more than one Game Winning Card in any Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text><strong>"Game Winning Pattern"</strong> means a specific array of numbers or other designations on a Card that, when Covered on the Card(s), entitles the player(s) to receive the Game Winning Prize.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(13)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Gaming Commission"</strong> means a Tribally designated entity responsible for Gaming regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(14)</num>
            <text><strong>"Gaming System" </strong>means all components, including electronic, computer, or other technologic equipment, that function together to aid the play of one or more games of Bingo including any Player Interfaces.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(15)</num>
            <text><strong>"NIGC"</strong> means the National Indian Gaming Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(16)</num>
            <text><strong>"NIGC Technical Standards"</strong> means the Technical Standards for Electronic, Computer, or Other Technologic Aids Used in the Play of Class II Games, 25 C.F.R. Part 547.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(17)</num>
            <text><strong>"Pattern"</strong> means, in the case of a Game Winning Pattern, an array of two or more numbers or other designations on a Card.  A Pattern for a Prize Winning Pattern must contain at least one number or other designation on a Card.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(18)</num>
            <text><strong>"Player Interface" </strong>means any component or components of a Gaming System, including an electronic or technologic aid such as terminals, player stations, handhelds, fixed units, etc. that directly enables player interaction in a game of Bingo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(19)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize"</strong> means anything of material value, including money, which is awarded to a player under the Rules of Play.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(20)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize Pool" </strong>means the cumulative amount of contributions paid by participants in one of more games of Bingo, which is used to fund prizes specified in the Rules of Play.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(21)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize Winning Card"</strong> means a Card on which a Prize Winning Pattern has been Covered, entitling a player to Claim an interim or consolation Prize under the Rules of Play.  There may be more than one Prize Winning Card in any Bingo game.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(22)</num>
            <text><strong>"Prize Winning Pattern"</strong> means a specific array of numbers or other designations that, when Covered on a Card(s), entitles the player(s) to receive an interim or consolation Prize.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(23)</num>
            <text><strong>"Random Number Generator (RNG)"</strong> means an electronic or mechanical method for determining numbers or other designations in a game of chance that must meet the applicable standards for randomness set forth in the NIGC Technical Standards or established by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(24)</num>
            <text><strong>"Rules of Play"</strong> means the specific rules controlling the play of the subject game of Bingo.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(25)</num>
            <text><strong>"Server" </strong>means a computer which controls one or more applications or environments within a Gaming System.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(26)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Gaming Facility"</strong> means the Casino, which is located on the Indian lands of the Tribe operated pursuant to the Tribe's Gaming Ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(27)</num>
            <text><strong>"Tribal Gaming Facility Manager (TGFM)"</strong> means the Casino Gaming Manager who operates the gaming facility for the Tribe.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.100 was formerly codified as 500.32</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.110</num>
        <heading>Classification Procedure</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Application Process</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Only a duly authorized representative of the GM may apply for a Classification Determination under this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The GM may apply for a Classification Determination at any time, but must do so before offering a new Gaming System for play under the following circumstances:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A</num>
              <text>The GM wishes to install a new Gaming System that is not the subject of an existing Classification Determination and is not otherwise permitted as a Class III game; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>The GM wishes to introduce a material modification to a previously approved Gaming System, including a Gaming system approved before the effective date of this Regulation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Although not required, the GM also may apply for a Classification Determination under this Regulation for a Gaming System approved by the Tribal Gaming Commission before the effective date of this Regulation.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Application Submission Requirements</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>To obtain a Classification Determination, the GM must submit an application to the Tribal Gaming Commission, which consists of the following documentation and information:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Request for a Classification Determination;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Certification by the vendor of the Gaming System that the Gaming System to be placed in the Tribal Gaming Facility:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Is within the criteria for a Class II game of Bingo under IGRA and this Regulation;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Complies in all respects with the specifications and standards set forth in the application<em>; </em>and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Complies with any applicable regulations concerning such Gaming System.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>A legal opinion that concludes that the Gaming System is a Class II game of Bingo under the IGRA played using a permitted electronic, computer or other technologic aids;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>GM's statement that, to the best of its knowledge and belief, the subject Gaming System meets the standards in these Regulations; [optional]</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>Designation of a point of contact authorized to provide additional information if required;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>Designation from the vendor of whether and where the Gaming System is already in play;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(G)</num>
              <text>Complete written description from the vendor of the Gaming System, including the operational characteristics and Rules of Play;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(H)</num>
              <text>Complete description of the method used for accepting Consideration from players, paying or distributing Prizes to winners, determining, retaining or paying any amounts to the operator or vendor from the Consideration or any other source, and the awarding or funding of Prize Pools;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(I)</num>
              <text>Copy of any of the vendor's sales or promotional literature for the Gaming System; [Optional]</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(J)</num>
              <text>For Gaming Systems already in play at the Tribal Gaming Facility, a complete list of the serial numbers or other identifiers of each Player Interface or other device used in the play of the Gaming System;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(K)</num>
              <text>Report of laboratory test(s), which must be addressed to the Tribal Gaming Commission, which were conducted that validate that the Gaming System meets the requirements of Sections B(1)(b)(ii) and (iii) of this Article, as well as the requirements of the NIGC Technical Standards found at 25 C.F.R. Part 547;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(L)</num>
              <text>Copies of any court or administrative decisions or other materials, supplied by the Gaming System vendor, which address the classification of the proposed Gaming System, if any;</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Submission of Additional Information</text>
          <text>Upon request of the Tribal Gaming Commission, the GM may be required to provide any further information or clarification the Tribal Gaming Commission deems necessary to make a Classification Determination.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.110 was formerly codified as 500.33</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.120</num>
        <heading>Classification Modifying Games</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Modification of Gaming Systems</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The GM shall submit to the Tribal Gaming Commission a request for a review of a Gaming System that is to be modified by providing a detailed description of the modification and how the modification affects the Gaming System.  If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that the modification represents a material change to the classification of the Gaming System, the GM must submit an application pursuant to part (2) of <cite path="5.01.120">this Section</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An application for a new Classification Determination shall not be required if the modification does not result in a material change to the operation of the Gaming System.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission shall maintain a list of modifications determined by the Tribal Gaming Commission to be non-material, which shall be updated periodically by the Tribal Gaming Commission as technology advances.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.120 was formerly codified as 500.34</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.130</num>
        <heading>Classification Criteria</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Factors to be Considered in Making Classification Determination</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The critical factors in determining whether a Gaming System is Class II are:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Whether the underlying game is a Class II game of Bingo; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Whether the electronic equipment utilized in connection with the game:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Is an electronic, computer or other technologic aid, which is permitted within Class II; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Causes the game to be an electromechanical facsimile of a game of chance.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>An electronic, computer or other technologic aid:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Is defined as electronic, computer, or other technologic equipment used in connection with a game of Bingo that:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Assists a player or the playing of a game;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Is not an electromechanical facsimile; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Is operated in accordance with applicable federal communications law.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Includes, but is not limited to, electronic, computer, or other technologic equipment used in connection with a Bingo game that:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>Broadens participation in the game;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>Facilitates communication between and among gaming sites; or</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Requires a player to play a game with or against other players rather than with or against a machine.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Examples include, but are not limited to, telephones, cables, televisions, screens, satellites, bingo blowers, electronic player stations and electronic Cards.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>An electromechanical facsimile is a game played in an electronic or electromechanical format that replicates a game of chance by incorporating all of the characteristics of the game, except when for a Class II game such as Bingo, the electronic or electromechanical format broadens participation by allowing multiple players to play with or against each other rather than with or against a machine.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Determination that Gaming System is Class II</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Bingo, as played using a Gaming System, will be determined to be a Class II game if it possesses the attributes of Bingo as set forth in the definition of Bingo in this Regulation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission has determined that the following attributes are required by the definition of Bingo:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The underlying game consists of:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(i)</num>
                <text>A set quantity of Draw numbers or other designations (hereinafter referred to as "Symbols");</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <text>A set number of Cards bearing an array or layout of numbers or other designations available for play in a particular game of Bingo;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <text>Predetermined Game Winning Pattern(s); and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <text>Prizes, including a Game Winning Prize and optional interim and consolation Prizes, as defined under the Rules of Play<em>.</em></text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>The Draw, if conducted using a Random Number Generator, must meet applicable standards for ensuring randomness as set forth in the NIGC Technical Standards or established by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Actual Prize values must be defined before a Prize can be awarded, but need not be defined before the start of a game.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>A game must be played by a minimum of two players.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission has determined that the following attributes are consistent with, <u>but not required by</u>, the definition of Bingo:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>The number of Symbols in a Draw is not fixed; it may be varied from game to game, in accordance with the Rules of Play.  Symbols may be displayed, without limitation, as numbers, letters, icons, any other graphic or other enhancement, or any combination thereof.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>A game may include any number of Cards.  The Card may be multi-dimensional.  Each Card must have an array or layout of symbols and contain at least two of the Draw symbols.  Game Winning Patterns and Prize Winning Patterns can be any configuration of matched symbols on the player's Card.  Interim and consolation Prizes also can be awarded for the absence of matched symbols.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>When playing Bingo, a Draw of a fixed number of Symbols may take place before Cards are purchased by, or distributed to, some or all of the players.  Players then compete in a given game by purchasing Cards and then revealing the designations on purchased Cards, so that the pre-drawn Symbols may be Covered.  Subsequent Draws may take place to assure that a Game Winning Pattern is achieved.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>Multiple Prizes may be specified in a game based on, but not necessarily limited to, different Patterns or the number of drawn Symbols required to achieve a specified Pattern.  There may be multiple winners, on multiple Cards.  Prize levels can also vary for the same Pattern as a function of the player's Consideration for the Card and/or how far the Draw has progressed.  Prizes may include interim or consolation Prizes where the Prize is based on the specific order in which the numbers are selected.  Progressive Prizes may also be awarded based on specified criteria reflecting sequence or specific characteristics of the Symbols Covered by the player.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>A player may play more than one Card in a game of Bingo.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>In determining whether Bingo, as played using a Gaming System, is a Class II game, the Tribal Gaming Commission should not apply any requirements that would:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(A)</num>
              <text>Limit the use of electronic aids to play Bingo, display Cards, Cover Symbols, identify Game or Prize Winning Patterns, or Claim Prizes;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(B)</num>
              <text>Limit the speed of play, Card configuration, or number of Draws in a game;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(C)</num>
              <text>Limit how or when Cards are distributed to players;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(D)</num>
              <text>Limit the sequence of a Draw;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(E)</num>
              <text>Limit how a player Claims a Prize;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(F)</num>
              <text>Limit the type of entertaining display on the Player Interface; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(G)</num>
              <text>Limit the maximum number of players.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.130 was formerly codified as 500.35</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.140</num>
        <heading>Classification Decisions</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Issuance of a Written Classification Determination</text>
          <text>If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that the Gaming System meets the criteria in Article 6 above, it shall issue a written Classification Determination and shall provide copies of such Classification Determination to the Tribal Council and the GM.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Issuance of an Unfavorable Determination</text>
          <text>If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that the Gaming System does not meet one or more of the criteria in Article 6 above, it shall issue a written decision specifically addressing the reasons for its determination and shall provide copies of such decision to the Tribal Council and the GM.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Finality of the Decision</text>
          <text>If the Tribal Gaming Commission determines that a Gaming System is not Class II for any reason, the decision of the Tribal Gaming Commission will be final and binding. The Tribal Gaming Commission may, in its discretion, allow a request for reconsideration upon a showing of new factual evidence or legal support.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.140 was formerly codified as 500.36</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.150</num>
        <heading>Installation of Gaming Systems</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Confirmation of Specifications</text>
          <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission requires the manufacturer or distributor of Gaming Systems intended for use in this jurisdiction to certify, in writing, that prior to delivery to the Tribe, each Gaming System:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Conforms precisely to the exact specifications of the system prototype tested and approved by the test laboratory.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Can be tested using one or more unique signatures, checksum values or similar technology for the operating programs used with the electronic computer, or other technologic aid.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Operates and plays in accordance with the NIGC Technical Standards, this Regulation and all other applicable Tribal Gaming Commission regulations.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Integrity of Seals</text>
          <text>Upon delivery of a Gaming System to the Tribal Gaming Facility, no one will break the seal of any delivery container, nor will any system be removed from the shipping container without the physical presence and authorization of a Tribal Gaming Commission official.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Use of Approved Locks</text>
          <text>The GM shall replace Player Interface locks with locks approved for use by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>System Modifications</text>
          <text>The GM shall develop policies and procedures to be approved by the Tribal Gaming Commission for installing, accessing, maintaining, repairing, and configuring systems in the same manner as set forth in Tribal Gaming Commission regulations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>Delivery of Gaming Systems</text>
          <text>At least ten (10) calendar days prior to shipping and delivery of a Gaming System, each manufacturer or distributor shall report in writing to the Tribal Gaming Commission the following information for each Player Interface to be used as part of the Gaming System:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The type of Player Interface (i.e. hand-held or fixed-base).</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The Player Interface serial number.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The manufacturer of the Player Interface.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The vendor from whom the Player Interface was acquired,  the means by which the Player Interface will be transported into the state, and the name and street address of any common carrier or other person transporting the Player Interface.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The date of shipping and anticipated delivery date.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Notice of New or Upgraded Software</text>
          <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission shall be notified by the GM of any subsequent purchases of any new or upgraded program software within ten (10) calendar days.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.150 was formerly codified as 500.37</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.160</num>
        <heading>Labeling of Approved Gaming Systems</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Serial Numbers</text>
          <text>Once a Gaming System has been determined to be Class II, the GM will provide a serial number and description of each Player Interface to the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Requirement for Seals or Labels</text>
          <text>The Tribal Gaming Commission shall affix a seal or a label on each of the internal components of each Player Interface to indicate proper determination. The seal or other label will be visible when the Player Interface door is open and will show the version number(s) or other unique identifier(s), as documented by the testing laboratory.  The seal or other label will be promptly removed from the Player Interface when the version number(s) of the software operated thereon are changed and a new seal or other label affixed showing the versions of the software in use; provided the new version(s) meet the standards established in this Regulation.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.160 was formerly codified as 500.38</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.170</num>
        <heading>Amendment/Repeal of Regulation</heading>
        <text>This Regulation may be amended or repealed upon approval by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.170 was formerly codified as 500.39</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>5.01.180</num>
        <heading>Effective Date</heading>
        <text>This Regulation shall take effect immediately upon adoption as approved by the Tribal Gaming Commission.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.180 was formerly codified as 500.39(a)</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
    <section>
      <num>5.01.190</num>
      <heading>Bingo (Non-Electronic)</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>For the purposes of <cite path="5.01.190">this chapter</cite>, the following definitions shall be used.  Words in the present tense include the future; the singular includes the plural; and the plural includes the singular.  The word "shall" is mandatory and the word "may" is permissive.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Bingo" means a game of chance in which players pay a consideration in order to participate, in which 75 numbered objects are available for selection, and those objects actually selected are selected on a random basis, and in which each player participates by means of cards sold, rented or used only at the time and place of the game, each card containing 5 rows of 5 spaces each, each space printed with a number from 1 to 75 except the central space, which is marked "FREE".  Winners are determined and prizes awarded on the basis of possessing a bingo card on which some combination of numbers are printed and conform to the number objects selected at random based on a predetermined winning arrangement.  "BINGO" as used in <cite path="5.01">this chapter</cite> shall not mean any game using free cards and donated prizes, if any, for which no payment of consideration is made by players.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Bingo Manager" means a person hired by the Tribe to conduct, organize and supervise all bingo and raffle occasions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"Bingo Occasion" means a single gathering or session at which a series of successive bingo games are played.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"Bingo Supplies and Equipment" means all cards, boards, sheets, markers, pads or other supplies, devices or other equipment designed for used in the conduct or play of bingo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>"Caller" means an individual who by means of a mechanical device randomly selects numbers and announces them to players.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>"Checker" means an individual who verifies a player's claim to have won a game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>"Class II Gaming" means class II gaming as defined by 25 U.S.C. §2703(7), including by not limited to bingo, raffles, and pull-tabs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>"Class III Gaming" means class III gaming as defined by U.S.C. §2703(8).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>"Council" means the governing body of the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>"Inventory Checker" means a designated person from the accounting office who shall be responsible for a monthly inventory check of the bingo supplies/materials.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>"Raffle" means a game of chance in which tickets are sold and a drawing for prizes is held, or in which the ticket is drawn by the purchaser and a determination of prize made based upon the ticket drawn.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>"Reservation" means all lands within the exterior boundaries of the Bad River Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>"Tribe" means the Bad River Band of the Lake Superior Chippewa Indians.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.01.190 was formerly codified as 500.4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.02</num>
    <heading>Bingo Manager</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.02.010</num>
      <heading/>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>There is hereby established the position of Tribal Bingo Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall be appointed by the Tribal Council.  The Tribal Bingo Manager shall be subject to the Bad River Gaming Operations Policies and Procedures and shall be supervised by the Gaming General Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>No person may commence work as Tribal Bingo Manager until such person has been licensed by the Tribe as a gaming manager.  Prior to licensing, the person's background shall be investigated, including his or her prior activities, criminal record, if any, reputation, habits, and associations; and a finding shall be made that hiring the individual will not pose a threat to the public interest or to the effective regulation of gaming, or create or enhance the dangers of unsuitable, unfair, or illegal practices, methods, or activities in the conduct of gaming.  Any applicant under consideration for hiring as Tribal Bingo Manager may be required to execute such releases as are necessary or convenient to obtain the information required under this paragraph.  The tribe's personnel manager shall be responsible for the thorough and efficient conduct of the investigation and may contract with such agencies or incur such expenses as are necessary or convenient to such end.  The personnel manager's findings and conclusions shall be made available to the tribal council and to the National Indian Gaming Commission prior to the issuance of any license.  The Bingo Manager shall not commence work until there is on file with the tribal personnel office evidence of a surety bond for the benefit of the Tribe in the amount of $25,000.00 to indemnify the Tribe for losses incurred by a breach of fiduciary or other duties arising hereunder.  The Tribe shall secure the bond for the Bingo Manager.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.02.010 was formerly codified as 501.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.02.020</num>
      <heading>Powers and Duties of Tribal Bingo Manager</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall have the following powers and duties:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>To conduct bingo operations in conformity with this ordinance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>To conduct raffles in conformity with this ordinance;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>To conduct other Class II gaming at any locale at which Bingo is played;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>To receive and deposit monies generated from operations described in subparagraphs (<em>a</em>), (<em>b</em>) and (<em>c</em>) with the Tribe's Treasurer, or authorized banking institutions;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>To report to the Tribal Council, on forms approved by the Tribal Council, on a monthly basis, unless required to do so more frequently by the Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>To supervise all personnel necessary to conduct operations under subparagraphs (<em>a</em>), (<em>b</em>) and (<em>c</em>).  No person shall be an employee of the Bingo when he or she is on the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council shall retain the duties of hiring any and all employees of the Bad River Bingo and the Chairman shall retain the duties of terminating any employees for good cause.  All employee relations shall be governed by the Bad River Gaming Operations Policies and Procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>To develop and enforce general polices, subject to Tribal Council approval, governing operations under subparagraphs (<em>a</em>), (<em>b</em>) and (<em>c</em>), which shall be followed by the Bingo Manager and the Bingo employees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>To insure compliance with Inventory/Cash controls systems developed by the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>To insure the security of Bingo, raffle, and other Class II gaming equipment and supplies in his custody or control and of Bingo, raffle and other Class II gaming revenues in his custody or control.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.02.020 was formerly codified as 501.2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.03</num>
    <heading>General Operating Provisions</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.010</num>
      <heading/>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Only the Bingo Manager or a person authorized by the Tribal Bingo Manager shall conduct bingo or act as a caller in the conduct of bingo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Bingo shall be conducted only on behalf of the tribal government and only on tribal premises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Purchase of a bingo card shall entitle each purchaser to a place on the Tribal premises where bingo is conducted with sufficient room in which to work the bingo card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager may, in his or her discretion, limit the number of persons allowed to purchase bingo cards at any one bingo occasion if there is not sufficient space or supplies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall hold not less than 106 bingo occasions within any calendar year.  The Tribal Bingo Manager may hold such further bingo occasions as the Council shall designate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall accept only a cash payment for any bingo card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall purchase such supplies and equipment as are necessary for the operation of bingo and consistent with the budget approved by the Tribal Council.  All equipment and supplies used in the conduct of bingo shall be owned by the Tribe.  The bingo equipment shall be maintained in good repair and sound condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Only the Tribal Bingo Manager and persons acting under his or her supervision may participate in the management or operations of any bingo occasion.  No other person, firm, corporation, consultant, or similar entity shall participate in the management of any bingo occasion.  Nothing herein shall prevent the Tribal Bingo Manager from entering into a contract for the televising of bingo occasions, however.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>No person under the age of 16 shall purchase or play a bingo card for any bingo game conducted pursuant to this ordinance unless accompanied on tribal premises by such person's parent or guardian.  No person under the age of 12 shall be allowed in the Tribal premises in which bingo is conducted during a bingo occasion</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>No alcoholic beverages or illegal drugs shall be allowed on Tribal premises where bingo is conducted during a bingo occasion.  Any person found possessing or using alcoholic beverages or illegal drugs during bingo occasions shall be removed from the premises and barred from further bingo occasions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>Bingo occasions shall be advertised by whatever lawful methods the Tribal Bingo Manager deems suitable and appropriate to attract a maximum number of players, consistent with the budget approved by the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall authorize the operation of concessions for the sale of food or refreshments by Tribal organizations under such terms and conditions as he or she deems appropriate.  No person or organization may sell any other merchandise on the premises where bingo is being conducted during a bingo occasion unless authorized by the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>Bingo cards shall be sold or rented by the Tribal Bingo Manager in the first instance only on the premises at which the bingo occasion is being conducted.  The Tribal Bingo Manager shall keep an accurate, separate count of the number of bingo cards which are sold, rented or used.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>No person employed in the operation of a Tribal Bingo occasion shall be permitted to purchase any bingo card, finance the purchase of any Bingo card, or share in the proceeds of any winnings for that occasion or participate in any other way as a player during that bingo occasion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(o)</num>
        <text>Nothing herein shall prevent the broadcast or televising of Tribal bingo occasions.  The Tribal Bingo Manager is hereby authorized to enter into a contract for the broadcast or televising of Tribal bingo occasions, provided that any such contract shall be approved by resolution of the Tribal Council before taking effect.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(p)</num>
        <text>Every month the Inventory Checker shall be responsible for taking a physical inventory of the supplies/materials to see if it matches the Bingo Manager's records.  Any discrepancies shall be reported to the Bingo Manager and Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(q)</num>
        <text>The Bingo Manager may conduct other Class II gaming at the times and places where Bingo is played or a raffle conducted.  Sections <cite path="5.03.010|(b)">5.03.010(<em>b</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(f)">(<em>f</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(g)">(<em>g</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(h)">(<em>h</em>)</cite> <cite path="5.03.010|(i)">(<em>i</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(j)">(<em>j</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(k)">(<em>k</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(l)">(<em>l</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(m)">(<em>m</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(n)">(<em>n</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(o)">(<em>o</em>)</cite>, and <cite path="5.03.010|(p)">(<em>p</em>)</cite>, and <cite path="5.03.020">5.03.020</cite> shall apply to the conduct of Class II gaming other than Bingo and raffles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(r)</num>
        <text>The Bingo Manager shall assure that ventilation, sanitary, and drinking water supply systems are all operating properly at all times and places when operation under subparagraphs <cite path="5.03.010|(a)">(<em>a</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.03.010|(b)">(<em>b</em>)</cite>, or <cite path="5.03.010|(c)">(<em>c</em>)</cite> occur.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.03.010 was formerly codified as 502.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.020</num>
      <heading>Prizes</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The amount and nature of prizes offered shall be determined for each bingo occasion by the Tribal Bingo Manager, provided that the prizes offered shall be commensurate with the generally accepted odds in bingo operations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Either cash prizes or merchandise prizes shall be allowed.  If a merchandise prize is offered, its stated value shall be the current retail price.  No merchandise prize shall be redeemable or convertible into cash, either directly or indirectly, by the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Prizes of alcoholic or fermented malt beverages, securities, or interests in real property are prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.03.020 was formerly codified as 502.2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.030</num>
      <heading>Method of Conduct</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall determine the type of game and prize for each game conducted during a bingo occasion.  The particular arrangement of numbers required on a bingo card in order to win and the amount of the prize for the game shall be clearly described and audibly announced to the players immediately before each game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Each bingo game shall be conducted in such a manner that the results are random and each person purchasing a card is afforded an equal opportunity to win, and all equipment and supplies used in the conduct of each game shall be designed and used in such a manner as to secure such result.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The objects to be drawn shall be as near the same size, shape, weight, balance, and all other relevant characteristics as is practicable so that at all times during the conduct of bingo each object possesses the capacity for equal agitation with any other object within the receptacle.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Seventy-five (75) objects, numbered consecutively "1" through  "75" inclusive, shall be used for the conduct of each game.  All 75 objects, and only 75 objects, shall be present in the receptacle at the beginning of each bingo game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The number on each object drawn shall be announced in a manner clearly audible to the persons present during the conduct of the game and shall be visually displayed as well.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Once removed from the receptacle during the conduct of a game, no object shall be returned to the receptacle until after the conclusion of that game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The receptacle and the caller shall be visible to the majority of persons present during the conduct of a game at all times.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.03.030 was formerly codified as 502.3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.03.040</num>
      <heading>Winners</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The winner of a bingo game shall be the person in possession of the bingo card with the numbers on it arranged in the manner announced for that game achieved with the least number of objects drawn and who audibly calls out "BINGO!"</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The bingo winner for each game shall be determined on the same day on which the bingo occasion is conducted.  Each prize shall be awarded within one week of the  bingo occasion for which the prize was offered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The numbers appearing on the winning card at the time a winner is determined shall be verified in the immediate presence of at least one disinterested person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>At the time a winner is determined, any person may call for a verification of all numbers and of the objects remaining in the receptacle not drawn.  Such verification shall be made in the presence of the Tribal Bingo Manager and at least one disinterested person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>When more than one person is found to be the winner of a bingo game, a cash prize shall be divided equally among the  winners.  When equal division of a merchandise prize is not possible, identical substitute prizes whose aggregate retail value is approximately equal to that of the designated prize shall be awarded.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.03.040 was formerly codified as 502.4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.04</num>
    <heading>Raffles</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.010</num>
      <heading>Conduct of Raffles</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A raffle shall be conducted only on Tribal premises, except as provided by <cite path="5.04.020|(b)|(2)">Section 5.04.020(<em>b</em>)(2)</cite>, by the Tribal Bingo Manager or a person authorized by the Tribal Bingo Manager or authorized by the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Only cash payment may be accepted for the purchase of a raffle ticket.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Supplies and equipment necessary for the operation of a raffle on behalf of the Tribe shall be purchased by the Tribal Bingo Manager as consistent with the budget approved by the Council.  Such supplies and equipment shall be owned by the Tribe</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Prizes of alcohol or fermented malt beverages, securities or interest in real property are prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.04.010 was formerly codified as 503.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.04.020</num>
      <heading>METHOD OF PLAY</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Types of Raffles.  There shall be two types of raffles which may be conducted:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Raffles in which tickets are sold to individuals, placed in a container and drawn to determine the winner, and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Raffles in which a fixed number of tickets, some which indicate the winners, are sold and drawn by the purchaser.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Tickets.  There shall be three types of tickets which shall be used for the raffles in subsection (<em>a</em>):</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>For raffles described in (<em>a</em>)(1) tickets shall be identical in form and numbered sequentially if the raffle tickets are only sold on the same day or night of the occasion and drawing of the winner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>For raffles described in (<em>a</em>)(1) and if the raffle tickets are sold over a period of time before the day or night of the drawing of the winner, the tickets shall be identical in form, contain the name and address of the Tribe or sponsoring organization, the price of the ticket, the date and place of the drawing and a place for the purchaser's name and address.  Sale of these raffle tickets off premises shall be permitted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>For raffles describe in (<em>b</em>)(2) raffle tickets shall be purchased in lots, with a fixed number of tickets and winning tickets in each lot, shall be of similar outward appearance and shall have concealed within the indices of winning what may be revealed by manipulation of the ticket by the purchasers after the purchase.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Play of Raffles:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall determine the type of raffle and the prize or prizes for each raffle, which shall be clearly described and available to raffle ticket purchasers at the time of purchase.  For raffles described in Section (<em>a</em>)(1), the odds per lot of tickets shall also be available.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Each raffle shall be conducted in such manner that the results are random and each person purchasing a ticket is afforded an equal opportunity to win, and all equipment and supplies used in the conduct of each raffle shall be designed and used in such a manner as to secure such a result.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Winners shall be determined according to the type of raffle and the rules of each raffle set by the Tribal Bingo Manager.  The purchaser of a ticket need not be present at the drawing to win a prize.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>All raffle drawings shall be held in public.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>All prizes shall be awarded.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.04.020 was formerly codified as 503.2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.05</num>
    <heading>Finances and Accounting</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.05.010</num>
      <heading>Annual Operating Budget</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Bingo, raffle, and other Class II gaming conducted at the locale at which Bingo is played shall be carried out in accordance with the annual operating budget adopted for that purpose.  Such budget shall detail the operational expenses of the operation and shall be prepared by the Tribal Bingo Manager and presented for approval by the Tribal Council at least one month before the commencement of the budget year.  The budget year shall begin January 1 of each year.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No expense may be incurred by the Tribal Bingo Manager except as provided for an in conformity with the annual operating budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council may, as circumstances warrant, amend the annual operating budget during the course of the year.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.05.010 was formerly codified as 504.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.05.020</num>
      <heading>Monthly Financial Report</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Bingo Manager shall prepare, sign, and submit to the Tribal Council a monthly financial report which shall include the following information for the preceding month:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The names of all persons employed in the conduct of bingo, raffles, and other associated Class II gaming;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The number and dates of all bingo occasions and raffles;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>An itemized statement of gross receipts from all bingo occasions and other Class II gaming;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>An itemized list of all expenditures;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>A statement showing the balance in the bingo account; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>An itemized list of transfers from the bingo account to other tribal accounts for administration, government and program expenditures.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.05.020 was formerly codified as 504.2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.05.030</num>
      <heading>Bingo Account</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Accounting Office shall create a special account into which bingo, raffle and other Class II gaming receipts shall be deposited.  Bingo, raffle, and associated Class II gaming receipts shall be deposited within three days of the Bingo or Raffle.  Gross receipts derived from the conduct of bingo, raffles, and other Class II gaming shall not be commingled with any other tribal funds.  Transfers from on the bingo account shall only be for one of the following purposes:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The payment of reasonable and necessary expenses incurred in connection with the conduct of bingo or raffles in conformity with the annual operating budget including the payment of any assessment under 25 U.S.C. §2717.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.05.030 was formerly codified as 504.3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.05.040</num>
      <heading>Audit</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The bingo, raffle, and other Class II gaming operations shall be subject to an annual outside audit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Included in such annual outside audit shall be all contracts for supplies, services, or concessions for a contract amount in excess of $25,000 annually, except contracts for professional legal or accounting services, related to bingo, raffle, and other class II gaming.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.05.040 was formerly codified as 504.4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.06</num>
    <heading>Class III Gaming</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.010</num>
      <heading>General Provisions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Class III gaming may be conducted pursuant to <cite path="5.06">this chapter</cite> at the following locations:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The log building located on U.S. Hwy. 2, at SE¼ NW¼ Sec. 32, T48N R2W.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any other location designated by Tribal Council resolution.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person, natural or legal, or association of persons, other than the Tribe, may conduct Class III gaming on the reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>All primary management officials and key employees of the Class III gaming operation shall be subject to the licensing provisions of <cite path="5.02.010|(c)">Section 5.02.010(<em>c</em>)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The chief management official of the Class III gaming operation shall be responsible for the development and implementation of policies to effectuate all standards for the conduct of games, prescribed by the Tribal Council including those policies and rules contained in <cite path="5.06.020">Section 5.06.020</cite> - <cite path="5.06.050">5.06.050</cite>, any tribal -state compact, and any National Indian Gaming Commission regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The chief management official of the Class III gaming operation shall be responsible for the conduct of all Class III gaming operations on the reservation and all Class II gaming operations conducted at Class III gaming facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The chief management official of the Class III gaming operation shall be subject to the same powers and duties with respect to the Class III gaming operation as the Bingo Manager is with respect to Bingo operations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Any person, natural or legal, and any association thereof, contracting with the Tribe to provide management service to the Class III gaming operation, or gaming related goods or services exceeding in value $10,000 per year, shall be required to obtain a gaming contractor license from the tribe, to be issued by the tribal chairman only after an investigation as provided <cite path="5.02.010|(c)" proof="needed">Section 5.02.010 (<em>c</em>)</cite> has been completed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>No member of the Tribal Council, and no spouse, parent, child or sibling of a member of the Tribal Council, may have any direct or indirect financial interest in the Class III gaming operation, nor may any such person or any employee of the Class III gaming operation receive any payment, gift, or gratuity of any kind from any gaming contractor licensed by the Tribe or from any person, natural or legal, or any association thereof, engaged in the provision of gaming goods or services, whether or not such person or association is currently providing any such goods or services to the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.06.010 was formerly codified as 505.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.020</num>
      <heading>Class III Gaming - Rules of Play</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person under 21 years of age may play or be permitted to play.  If any person below the age of 21 years plays and otherwise qualifies for a prize or winnings, the prize or winning shall not be paid, and the estimated amount wagered during the course of the game shall be returned to the minor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person under the age of 21 shall be permitted access to any portion of any facility in which any Class III game is conducted, except for purposes of employment pursuant to Section V.B., or to gain access to the Tribe's non-gaming facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The chief management official of the Class III gaming operation shall cause to be posted at places where notice is likely that an announcement is most visible that persons under the age of  21 may not participate in gaming.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>No person who is visibly intoxicated may play any Class III game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>No credit shall be extended by the Tribe or any of its agents or employees for the conduct of gaming.  No person shall offer any other person credit for a fee, however calculated for the conduct of gaming, except that an automatic teller machine that accepts bank cards or credit cards may be installed upon Class III gaming premises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>No alcoholic beverages may be sold at the Class III facility for the purpose of off-premises consumption.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Electronic games of chance shall be installed and operated pursuant to section XV of the current Compact entered into by the Tribe and the State of Wisconsin</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Blackjack shall be conducted pursuant to Section XVI of the current Compact entered into by the Tribe and the State of Wisconsin.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Pulltab or break open ticket games shall be conducted pursuant to the most recent published standards of the North American Gaming Regulators Association.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>If a player has a dispute concerning the conduct of a game, he or she shall have the right to a resolution of the dispute by the chief management official on the premises at the time the dispute arises.  The dispute shall be resolved upon notification of the management official involved, after hearing from the aggrieved player and any involved Class III facility employee involved.  The decision of the management official shall be final.  If the dispute involves the chief management official on the premises, it shall be resolved within five working days by the tribal chairman or, in his absence, the vice-chairman, after hearing from the aggrieved player and the involved management official.  The decision of the chairman or vice-chairman shall be final.  Copies of <cite path="5.06.020">this section</cite> of <cite path="5.06">this chapter</cite> shall be kept at the Class III facility and shall be made available to any customer of the Class III facility upon request.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.06.020 was formerly codified as 505.2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.030</num>
      <heading>Class III Gaming - Tax Withholding</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Federal income tax shall be withheld from any prize or winnings in those cases where such withholding is required by the United States Internal Revenue Code.  In all such cases, Wisconsin income tax shall also be withheld except on payments to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Enrolled members of the Tribe, or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Individuals who certify to the Tribe, on forms that the chief management official shall assure are available, that they are not legal residents of the State of Wisconsin, unless such individuals are subject to Wisconsin income tax on such winnings under ch. 71, Wis. Stat., for the calendar year in which the payment is made.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The amount of Wisconsin income taxes withheld under subsection (a) shall be the amount of winnings multiplied by 6.93% (.0693), or the highest Wisconsin income tax rate applicable to individuals under Section 71.06(1), whichever is higher.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Taxes withheld under <cite path="5.06.030">this section</cite> shall be deposited with the United States Internal Revenue Service and the Wisconsin Department of Revenue as provided by federal and state law.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.06.030 was formerly codified as 505.3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.040</num>
      <heading>Class Gaming - Employees</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Restrictions on employee and elected official gaming:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>No person employed at the Class Ill facility in a management position may participate, directly or indirectly, as a player in any game that they have a direct supervisory responsibility over at the Class Ill facility.  This prohibition shall not include the any employee of the Band as it concerns the play of non-house banked table games. No person who has been employed at the Class III facility in a management position may participate, directly or indirectly, as a player in any game that they have a direct supervisory responsibility over at the Class III facility until 30 days have elapsed since the person's last day of such employment. Management employees affected by this provision shall be identified and listed by the Class III facility manager. The management employee list shall be presented to the Tribal Council for approval. The management employee list shall be updated by the Class III facility manager and presented to the Tribal Council as personnel changes occur. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary, in no instance shall the General Manager, Assistant General manager, Internal Auditor, MIS Manager, MIS Assistant Manager participate as a player in any game at the Class III facility except non-house banked table games.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Non-management employees of the Class III facility may participate as players in games (with the exception of pull tabs and progressive gaming devices not linked to external progressive systems) at the Class III facility, subject to restrictions for non-management employee play which may be established by Casino management and approved by the Bad River Tribal Council. Non-key employees may play only those progressive gaming devices which are linked to external progressive systems.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Elected officials of the Bad River Tribal Council shall not participate in any drawings, raffles or other promotions of the Class III facility. Unless otherwise prohibited in <cite path="5.06.040">this section</cite>, Elected Officials may participate in any game at the Class III facility.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person employed at the Class III facility may participate directly or indirectly as a player in any game at the Class III facility.  No person who has been employed at the Class III facility may participate, directly or indirectly, as a player in any game at the Class III until 30 days have elapsed since the person's last day of such employment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>No person employed at the Class III facility may have any direct or indirect interest in, or be employed by, any person who has entered a gaming-related contract with the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>No person under the age of 18 may be employed at the Class III facility in any position related to the conduct of gaming.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.06.040 was formerly codified as 505.4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.050</num>
      <heading>Class III Gaming - Records and Audits</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Accounting Office shall maintain for at least seven years, and shall permit the authorized agents of the State of Wisconsin to inspect and copy, the following records:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>All accounting records, which shall be kept on a double entry system of accounting, including detailed, supporting and subsidiary records.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Revenues, expenses, assets, liabilities and equity by game at each location where any component of Class III gaming including ticket sales, is conducted.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Daily cash transactions for each game at each location at which any component of Class III gaming is conducted, including by not limited to transactions relating to each gaming table bank, game drop box and gaming room bank.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>For electronic games of chance, analytic reports which, by each machine, compare actual hold percentages to theoretical hold percentages.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Contracts, correspondence and other transaction documents relating to all vendors and contractors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Records of all Tribal enforcement activities relating to gaming operated under this Compact.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>All audits prepared by or on behalf of the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Personnel office shall  maintain for at least seven years, and shall permit the authorized agents of the State of Wisconsin to inspect and copy, the following records:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Personnel information on all Class III gaming employees or agents, including complete sets of each employee's fingerprints, employee photographs, and employee profiles and background investigations, except that employee work schedules shall be maintain for a period of at least 2 years.  This provision shall not include personnel records of tribal members as to matters that are not related to gaming.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Records of background investigations and determinations under Section IX of the current compact between the Tribe and State of Wisconsin.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>At the close of each fiscal year, the chief management official of the Class III facility shall assure that an independent certified public accountant has been engaged to conduct a financial audit of the books and records of the Tribe's Class III gaming operations.  The audit shall be completed within 90 days after the close of the fiscal year.  The chief management official shall assure that copies of any audit reports and management letters are forwarded to the Wisconsin State Auditor and to the Lottery Board.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>For the fiscal year including December 1991, and each subsequent fiscal year which includes the December of an odd-numbered year, the chief management official of the Class III facility shall assure that a qualified independent security auditor has been engaged to conduct a security audit.  The audit shall review and evaluate the effectiveness, adequacy, and enforcement of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Physical systems and administrative policies and procedures controlling access to non-public offices, warehouses, and computer rooms relating to the conduct of gaming under this Compact.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Physical systems and administrative policies and procedures for handling cash and redemption of winning tickets or credit statements issued by electronic games of chance from their receipt by the Tribe to payment of the player, including procedures for receiving and routing incoming prize claims.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Policies, procedures and practices to prevent theft, loss or destruction of materials, equipment, or supplies associated with any of the games authorized by this compact, including records required to be created and maintained by this Compact.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Policies, procedures and practices to ensure the randomness, accuracy, integrity and reliability of games operated pursuant to this Compact.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Fitness and integrity of computer software utilized for financial accounting and conduct of gaming under this Compact.  The chief management official shall assure that within 90 days of the close of fiscal year copies of any audit reports and management letters are sent to the Wisconsin State Auditor and Lottery Board.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Audits shall be conducted in accordance with Section XII (c) of the current Compact entered into by the Tribe and the State of Wisconsin.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.06.050 was formerly codified as 505.5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.060</num>
      <heading>Class III Gaming - Finances and Accounting</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The chief management official of the Class III gaming operation shall submit to the Tribal Council a monthly financial report which shall include the following information for the preceding month</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Accounting Office shall create a special account into which Class III receipts shall be deposited.  Class III receipts shall not be commingled with any other tribal funds.  Checks drawn on the Class III account shall be only be for the following purposes</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Class III gaming operations shall be subject to an annual outside audit which shall include all contracts for supplies, services, or concessions for a contract amount in excess of $25,000 annually, except for professional legal or accounting services, related to Class III gaming.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.06.060 was formerly codified as 505.6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.070</num>
      <heading>Class III Gaming - Off Reservation</heading>
      <reason>Reserved</reason>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.06.070 was formerly codified as 505.6m</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.07</num>
    <heading>Violations</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.07.010</num>
      <heading>Prohibited Activities</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful and prohibited activity for any person to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Violate the terms of <cite path="5.07">this chapter</cite> or of <cite path="5.08">Chapter 5.08</cite> in any way; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Conduct a bingo game or occasion, raffle, other Class III gaming, or Class III gaming within the boundaries of the reservation except in conformity with this ordinance; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Act or scheme in any way to influence the conduct or result of any gaming activity or the determination of the winner thereof; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Act or scheme in any way to deprive the Tribe of the income or proceeds of any potion thereof from gaming activities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Misrepresent on an application, form, or in any interview any material fact related to his or her qualifications for a license under <cite path="5.07">this chapter</cite> or for any gaming-related employment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Possess or use any mechanical, electrical, optic, radio, infrared, video, or other device, including but not limited to cameras, transmitters, receivers, calculators, computers, or any kind of artificial or enhanced intelligence, in the Class III gaming location buildings and all auxiliary equipment whether or not located within the Class III gaming buildings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>(1) Issue any check or other order for payment which at the time of issuance he or she intends shall not be paid.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any of the following is prima facie evidence that the person at the time he or she issued the check or other order for the payment of money, intended it should not be paid</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Engage, while in the Class III gaming location buildings or on the Class III gaming location grounds, in any violent, abusive, indecent, profane, boisterous, unreasonably loud or otherwise disorderly conduct under circumstances in which the conduct tends to cause or provoke a disturbance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Disobey an exclusion order issued under <cite path="5.07.040">Section 5.07.040</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.07.010 was formerly codified as 506.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.07.020</num>
      <heading>Penalty</heading>
      <text>For commission of any of the prohibited activities in <cite path="5.07.010">Section 5.07.010</cite>, the violator shall be subject to the following penalties:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A civil remedial forfeiture of up to $5,000.00 for each violation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Seizure and forfeiture of all property used in the violation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Discipline or discharge from Tribal employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Referral to state or federal authorities for criminal prosecution; and/or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Such civil remedies as the Tribe may have available to recover any losses caused by or associated with such violations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>For a violation of <cite path="5.07.010|(c)">Section 5.07.010(<em>c</em>)</cite>, <cite path="5.07.010|(d)">(<em>d</em>)</cite>, or <cite path="5.07.010|(f)">(<em>f</em>)</cite>, seizure and forfeiture of all winnings resulting from the violation.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.07.020 was formerly codified as 506.2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.07.030</num>
      <heading>Enforcement</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Jurisdiction is hereby conferred upon the Tribal Court over actions for violation of this ordinance under the procedures set forth in the Tribal Court Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The provisions of this ordinance shall be enforced by all Tribal law enforcement officers.  In addition, federal, state, and local law enforcement officers are hereby authorized to enforce the provisions of this ordinance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>In addition to the penalties set forth in <cite path="5.07.020">Section 5.07.020</cite>, the court, upon conviction, shall order payment of appropriate court costs.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.07.030 was formerly codified as 506.3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.07.040</num>
      <heading>Exclusion</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any person may be excluded from the buildings and grounds of any Class III location for any reason, including but not limited to, disorderly or disruptive behavior, interference with other patrons, suspicion of a violation of any section of this ordinance, suspicion of possession any controlled substance or substance that it is illegal for the person to be excluded to possess, intoxication, being under the influence of any drug or alcohol, or any behavior that may tend to diminish the peaceful enjoyment of the gaming facilities by the patrons, or that may tend to diminish patronage.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The supervisor on duty may exclude any person for a 24 hour period, by orally and in writing, notifying the person of the exclusion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The gaming manager may permanently exclude any person by orally and in writing notifying the person of the exclusion.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.07.040 was formerly codified as 506.4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.07.050</num>
      <heading>Implied Consent</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Every person entering the Class III gaming facility buildings or grounds irrevocably consents to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The personal and subject matter jurisdiction of the Bad River Tribal Court regarding all alleged violations of <cite path="5.07">this chapter</cite> and all civil claims that may be brought by the Bad River Tribe to recover any losses caused by or associated with such violations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Temporary detention, questioning, and search upon reasonable suspicion that a violation of <cite path="5.07">this chapter</cite> has occurred, seizure of any property reasonably believed to be used in the violation, and forfeiture of the same.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The gaming manager shall place a notice of the provision of this <cite path="5.07.050">Section 5.07.050</cite> at all entrances to the buildings of the Class III facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.07.050 was formerly codified as 506.5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.07.060</num>
      <text>The Bad River Tribal Bingo and Raffle Control Ordinance is hereby repealed as of the date of enactment hereof.  All other ordinances or portions thereof inconsistent or in conflict with this ordinance are hereby repealed to the extent of the inconsistency only.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.07.060 was formerly codified as 506</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.08</num>
    <heading>Gaming Control Ordinance Part II</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.010</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Council of the Bad River Band of Lake Superior Tribe of Chippewa Indians (hereinafter "Tribe"), empowered by the Bad River constitution to enact ordinances, hereby enacts this ordinance in order to set the terms for Class II and III gaming.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.010 was formerly codified as 550.1</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.020</num>
      <heading>Gaming Authorized</heading>
      <text>Class II and III gaming as defined in the Indian Gaming Regulatory Act, P.L. 100-447, 25 U.S.C. Section 2703(7)(A) and (8)(IGRA) and by the regulations promulgated by the National Indian Gaming Commission at 25 C.F.R. sections 502.3 and 502.4 (as published in the Federal Register at 57 FR 12382-12393, April 9, 1992) is hereby authorized.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.020 was formerly codified as 550.2</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.030</num>
      <heading>Ownership of Gaming</heading>
      <text>The Tribe shall have the sole propriety interest in and responsibility for the conduct of any gaming operation on the Bad River Reservation or authorized by this ordinance.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.030 was formerly codified as 550.3</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.040</num>
      <heading>Use of Gaming Revenue</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Net revenues from Class II and III gaming shall be used only for the following purposes:  to fund tribal government operations and programs, provide for the general welfare of the Tribe and its members, promote tribal economic development, donate to charitable organizations, or help fund operations of local government agencies.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>If the Tribe elects to make per capita payments to tribal members, it shall authorize such payments only upon approval of a plan submitted to the Secretary of the Interior under 25 U.S.C. subsection 2710(b)(3).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.040 was formerly codified as 550.4</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.050</num>
      <heading>Audit</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Tribe's gaming manager shall cause to be conducted annually an independent audit of gaming operations and shall submit the resulting audit reports to the National Indian Gaming Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>All gaming related contracts that result in the purchase of supplies, services, or concessions in excess of $25,000.00 annually, except contracts for professional, legal and accounting services shall be subjected to the audit that is described in subsection (<em>a</em>) above.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.050 was formerly codified as 550.5</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.060</num>
      <heading>Protection of the Environment and Public Health and Safety</heading>
      <text>Class II and III gaming facilities shall be constructed, maintained and operated in a manner that adequately protects the environment and the public health and safety.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.060 was formerly codified as 550.6</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.070</num>
      <heading>Licenses for Key Employees and Primary Management Officials</heading>
      <text>The Tribe's gaming manager shall ensure that the policies and procedures set out in <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite> are implemented with respect to key employees and primary management officials employed at any Class II or Class III gaming enterprise operated on Indian lands.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Application Forms</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The following notice shall be placed on the application form for a key employee or a primary management official before that form is filled out by an applicant:</text>
          <text>In compliance with the Privacy Act of 1974, the following information is provided:  Solicitation of the information on this form is authorized by 25 U.S.C. 2701 et seq.  The purpose of the requested information is to determine the eligibility of individuals to be employed in a gaming operation.  The information will be used by Tribal government and staff and National Indian Gaming Commission members and staff who have need for the information in the performance of their official duties.  The information may be disclosed to appropriate Federal, Tribal, State, local, or foreign law enforcement and regulatory agencies when relevant to civil, criminal or regulatory investigations or prosecutions or when pursuant to a requirement by a Tribe or the National Indian Gaming Commission in connection with a hiring or firing of an employee, the issuance or revocation of a gaming license, or investigations of activities while associated with a tribe or a gaming operation.  Failure to consent to the disclosures indicated in this notice will result in the Tribe's being unable to hire you in primary management official or key employee position.</text>
          <text>The disclosure of your Social Security Number (SSN) is voluntary.  However, failure to supply a SSN may result in errors in processing your application.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The following notice shall be placed on the application form for a key employee or a primary management official before that form is filled out by an applicant.</text>
          <text>A false statement on any part of your application may be grounds for not hiring you, or for firing you after you begin work.  Also, you may be punished by forfeiture, fine or imprisonment under both tribal and federal law.  (U.S. Code, title 18, section 1001.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The following notice shall be placed on the application form for a key employee or a primary management official before that form is filled out by an applicant.</text>
          <text>If you are hired, you may be hired conditionally, pending the completion of a background investigation and eligibility for licensure determination.  If for any reason you do not receive a favorable background investigation report or eligibility determination by the completion of your 90th day of employment, your employment will be terminated.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Background Investigations</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's personnel director shall request from each primary management official and from each key employee all of the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Full name, other names used (oral or written), social security number(s), birth date, place of birth, citizenship, gender, all languages (spoken or written);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Currently and for the previous five years:  business and employment positions held, ownership interests in those businesses, business and residence addresses, and drivers license numbers;</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>The names and current addresses of at least three personal references, including one personal reference who was acquainted with the applicant during each period of residence listed under paragraph (1)(b) of <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite>;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Current business and residence telephone numbers;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>A description of any existing and previous business relationships with Indian tribes, including ownership interests in those businesses;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>A description of any existing and previous business relationships with the gaming industry generally, including ownership interest in those businesses;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>The name and address of any licensing or regulatory agency with which the person has filed an application for a license or permit related to gaming, whether or not such license or permit was granted;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <text>For each felony for which there is an ongoing prosecution or a conviction, the charge, the name and address of the court involved, and the date and disposition if any;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(vii)</num>
              <text>For each misdemeanor conviction or ongoing misdemeanor prosecution (Excluding minor traffic violation), within 10 years of the date of the application, the name and address or the court involved and the date and disposition;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(viii)</num>
              <text>For each criminal charge (excluding minor traffic charges), whether or not there is a conviction, if such criminal charge is within 10 years of the date of the application and is not otherwise listed pursuant to paragraph (1)(h) or (1)(i) of <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite> the criminal charge, the name and address of the court involved and the date and disposition;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ix)</num>
              <text>The name and address of any licensing or regulatory agency with which the person has filed an application for an occupational license or permit, whether or not such license or permit was granted;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(x)</num>
              <text>A current photograph;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(xi)</num>
              <text>Any other information the Tribe deems relevant; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(xii)</num>
              <text>Fingerprints consistent with procedures adopted by the Tribe according to 25 C.F.R. subsection 522.2(h).</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's personnel director shall conduct an investigation sufficient to make a determination under subsection (<em>d</em>) below.  The investigation may be conducted prior to any hiring of the person for a key employee or primary management official position.  In conducting a background investigation the Tribe or its agent shall promise to keep confidential the identify of each person interviewed in the course of the investigation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Eligibility Determination</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Tribe shall review a person's prior activities, criminal record, if any, and reputation, habits and associations to make a finding concerning the eligibility of a key employee or primary management official for employment in a gaming operation.  If the Tribe determines that employment of the person poses a threat to the public interest or to the effective regulation of gaming, or creates or enhances dangers of unsuitable, unfair, or illegal practices and methods and activities in the conduct of gaming, a tribal gaming operation shall not employ that person in a key employee or primary management official position.  This determination may be made prior to any hiring of the person for a key employee or primary management official position.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Under no circumstances shall any individual be employed directly in the operation or conduct of Class III gaming who has been convicted of, or entered a plea of guilty or no contest to, any of the following, unless the person has been pardoned:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>A felony, other than a felony conviction for an offense under subdiv. (<em>B</em>), (<em>C</em>), or (<em>D</em>), during the immediately preceding 10 years.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Any gambling-related offense.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Fraud or misrepresentation in any connection.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>A violation of any provision of chapters. 562 or 565, Wis. Stats., a rule promulgated by the Lottery Board or Wisconsin Racing Board, or a Tribal ordinance regulating or prohibiting gaming.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The prohibition contained in the preceding paragraph may be waived by the Tribal Council, by resolution, if the applicant or employee demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Tribal Council evidence of sufficient rehabilitation and present fitness.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Procedures for Forwarding Applications and reports for Key Employees and Primary Management Officials to the National Indian Gaming Commission</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>When a key employee or primary management official begins work at a gaming operation authorized by this ordinance, the Tribe's personnel director shall forward to the National Indian Gaming Commission a completed application for employment and conduct the background investigation and make the determination referred to in subsection D of <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite>, unless already completed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's personnel director shall forward the report referred to in subsection (<em>f</em>) of <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite> to the National Indian Gaming Commission within 60 days after an employee begins work or within 50 days of the approval of this ordinance by the Chairman of the National Indian Gaming Commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The gaming operation shall not employ as  a key employee or primary management official, a person who does not receive a license within 90 days of hiring.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Report to the National Indian Gaming Commission</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Pursuant to the procedures set out in subsection <em>(e)</em> of <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite>, the Tribe shall prepare and forward to the National Indian Gaming Commission an investigative report on each background investigation.  An investigative report shall include all of the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Steps taken in conducting a background investigation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Results obtained;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Conclusions reached; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>The bases for those conclusions.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's personnel director shall submit, with the report, a copy of the eligibility determination made under subsection D of <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>If a license is not issued to an applicant, the Tribe shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Notify the National Indian Gaming Commission; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Forward copies of its eligibility determination and investigation report (if any) to the National Indian Gaming Commission for inclusion in the Indian Gaming Individuals Records System.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>With respect to key employees and primary management officials, the Tribe shall retain applications for employment and reports (if any) of background investigations for inspection by the Chairman of the National Indian Gaming Commission or his or her designee for no less than three (3) years from the date of termination of employment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Granting A Gaming License</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Council shall issue all gaming licenses.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>If, within a thirty (30) day period after the National Indian Gaming Commission receives a report, the National Indian Gaming Commission notifies the tribe that it has no objection to the issuance of a license pursuant to a license application filed by a key employee or a primary management official for whom the tribe has provided an application and investigative report to the National Indian Gaming Commission, the Tribe's personnel director may recommend that the Tribal Council issue a license to such applicant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Tribe shall respond to a request for additional information from the Chairman of the National Indian Gaming Commission concerning a key employee or a primary management official who is the subject of a report.  Such a request shall suspend the 30-day period under paragraph (<em>g</em>)(2) of <cite path="5.08.070">this section</cite> until the Chairman of the National Indian Gaming Commission receives the additional information.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>If, within the thirty (30) day period described above the National Indian Gaming Commission provides the Tribe with a statement itemizing objections to the issuance of a license to a key employee or to a primary management official for whom the tribe has provided an application, the Tribe shall reconsider the application taking into account the objections itemized by the National Indian Gaming Commission.  The Tribe's personnel director shall supply to the Tribal Council the Native Indian Gaming Commission statement, prior to council action on the license.  The Tribal Council shall make the final decision whether to issue a license to such applicant.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>License Suspension</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>If, after the issuance of a gaming license, the Tribe receives from the National Indian Gaming Commission reliable information indicating that a key employee or a primary management official is not eligible for employment under subsection (d) above, the Tribe's personnel director shall suspend such license and shall notify in writing the licensee of the suspension and the proposed revocation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Tribe's personnel director shall notify the licensee of a time and a place for a hearing on the proposed revocation of a license, which shall be conducted before the Tribal Council under rules as it may prescribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>After a revocation hearing, the Tribal Council shall decide to revoke or to reinstate a gaming license.  The decision of the Tribal Council shall be final.  The Tribe shall notify the National Indian Gaming Commission of is decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.070 was formerly codified as 550.7</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.080</num>
      <heading>License Locations</heading>
      <text>The Tribe shall issue a separate license to each place, facility, or location on Indian lands where Class II or Class III gaming is conducted under this ordinance.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.080 was formerly codified as 550.8</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.08.090</num>
      <heading>Supercedence</heading>
      <text>To the extent that any section of <cite path="5.01">Chapter 5.01</cite>, Bad River ordinances, is inconsistent with any section of <cite path="5.08">this chapter</cite>, <cite path="5.08">this chapter's</cite> section controls.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="Prior Codifications">§5.08.090 was formerly codified as 550.9</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <text>
      <strong>LEGISLATIVE HISTORY</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Amended by  #9-21-12-</text>
    <text>Amended by Resolution #11-29-07-189   Amended by: #11-29-07-190   Amended by: #12-29-04-31;</text>
    <text>Amended by: #12-29-04-30;     Amended by:  #12-29-04-29;    Amended by: #3-21-03-59;</text>
    <text>Amended by: #6-19-02-295;     Amended by:  #9-18-01-157;    Amended by: #7-2-01-119B;</text>
    <text>Amended by: #3-01-01-49;      Amended by: #1-5-00-369;    Amended by: #4-8-98-132;</text>
    <text>Amended by: #9-6-93-81;       Amended by: #10-7-92-154;     Amended by: #9-20-91-151;</text>
    <text>Amended by: #4-1-87-39;       Adopted by Resolution #6-4-86-34</text>
  </container>
</container>
